<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-16T17:38:32+11:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">My Tech Blog</title><subtitle>A whole heap of tech talk</subtitle><author><name>Anurag Purkayastha</name></author><entry><title type="html">Designing An App - Part 1</title><link href="/Designing-An-App-Part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing An App - Part 1" /><published>2021-10-11T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2021-10-11T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>/Designing-An-App-Part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/Designing-An-App-Part-1/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/monopoly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of monopoly board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I had to complete a week long coding test for a job application I
submitted. Fortunately, the company found my submission of acceptable quality
and I made it through to the next round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about the design process I undertook to program the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-game&quot;&gt;The Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game was a customised version of the popular game, Monopoly. The rules of the game are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four players who take turns in the following order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Billy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charlotte&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sweedal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each player starts with $16.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everybody starts on GO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You get $1 when you pass GO (this excludes your starting move)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you land on a property, you must buy it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you land on an owned property, you must pay rent to the owner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the same owner owns all property of the same colour, the rent is doubled&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once someone is bankrupt, whoever has the most money remaining is the winner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are no chance cards, jail or stations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The board wraps around (i.e. you get to the last space, the next space is the first space)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The squares of the board were provided as a JSON file named &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;board.json&lt;/code&gt;. This file was to be read in to the program. Another important implementation note is that the game was &lt;strong&gt;deterministic&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning that there were set moves for each player which were also to be read in to the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;task&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The task I was given to complete was to design a program that simulates the gameplay given the moves and board and determine the winner of each game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition the following were also required:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much money does everybody finish with?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What locations does everybody finish on?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;application-design&quot;&gt;Application Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started programming in my life, I would be very inclined to start coding something straight away without any planning (or more accurately, I would plan as I was writing the code).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with more experience I have come to understand that planning the approach before typing any code makes things a whole lot easier. So, this is exactly what I did to tackle this test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;object-oriented-progamming&quot;&gt;Object Oriented Progamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This application was a perfect opportunity for object oriented programming because there are different &lt;strong&gt;objects&lt;/strong&gt; that could be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about the game, what objects can there be? Well, there are &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Players&lt;/code&gt; who earn money from rent, spend money to buy property or paying rent. There are also &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; objects that represent each square on the board (GO, property etc). Finally, a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; object can be used to create a game of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Players&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Squares&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summarising, the main objects are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Players&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Squares (of the board)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game - the main object which creates a game with a board of squares and players.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;players&quot;&gt;Players&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a game of monopoly, each player has a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;money&lt;/code&gt; that they spend on
buying property and paying rent. The amount of money also determines the winner
of the game. For the purpose of designing a simulation, a Player can also keep track of its own &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;position&lt;/code&gt; on the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the attributes that a Player of the game has are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Total amount of money&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current position on the board&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can be the &lt;em&gt;fields&lt;/em&gt; of a Player object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can a player do? Well, they can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend money - for rent or buying property&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Earn money - from rent or passing GO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check if they are bankrupt - in which case the game ends if any player goes bankrupt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These can be the &lt;em&gt;methods&lt;/em&gt; of a Player object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;squares&quot;&gt;Squares&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real monopoly game board is made up of board &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Squares&lt;/code&gt;, with each square
containing a property (that can be bought or rented) or GO. So, extracting from 
reality, we can design a board of the simulation to be made up of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt;
objects with similar properties. That is, each Square can be a property that can
be bought (owned) and rented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each Square has the following attributes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Name (Property name)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Price&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type (“property” or “go”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Owner (when bought)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rent (when bought).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; has the following abilties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being bought&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double the rent (when a player owns all the properties of the same colour)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check if the property is owned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;game&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we have &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Players&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Squares&lt;/code&gt;. We can implement a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; object that
initialises and runs a “game” in the simulation. For example, a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; can
create the squares and players and implmement the gameplay logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using these ideas, a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Game&lt;/code&gt; object can have the following abilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check if any player is bankrupt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Announce the winning player and the final results when game ends.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep track of the current player.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move the current player the predetermined amount of moves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check if any player owns all properties of one particular colour and double
the rent of all corresponding properties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gameplay-logic&quot;&gt;Gameplay Logic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the application objects have been designed, we can start thinking about
the actual logic of the gameplay. That is, we can think about a high level idea
of how a game is played. The algorithm that I used is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check if any player is bankrupt or if there are no more moves left to play.
    a. If any condition is met, then announce the final results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get the current Player whose turn it is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get the amount of moves, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;, that the current Player should move.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Move the Player &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; moves away from the Player’s current position on the
board.
    a. If the destination square that is &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; moves away from the Player’s
    current position is beyond the total number of squares, then wrap around.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Check if the square the Player has landed on is owned.
    a. If it is, then pay rent to the owner.
    b. If it is not, then Player buys the property. The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;owner&lt;/code&gt; attribute of the
    square will be updated to be the Player.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go to step 1.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps above are essentially the steps for one turn for a Player. We can
implement these steps for each Player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post we have covered the design of the application by designing game
objects which creates some modularity. This helps to build, debug, test and
extend the application. We have also gone over the game play logic by thinking
about the steps that a turn for a Player will take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about the game simulation, but it also covers thinking about
programs using Object Oriented Programming design. It shows how breaking up a
seemingly complex program can simplify the implementation and maintenance of the
application by breaking the program down into smaller parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Part 2, I’ll briefly go over some technical details of the implementation
which will essentially be an outline of the files and unit test.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anurag Purkayastha</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to my tech blog!</title><link href="/welcome-to-my-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to my tech blog!" /><published>2021-10-08T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2021-10-08T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>/welcome-to-my-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="/welcome-to-my-blog/">&lt;p&gt;This is my blog which will be about a whole heap of tech stuff! From linux to programming to web development to networking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be adding posts to this blog as time allows because I am also working ;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be covering topics that I find particularly interesting. For example, I’m currently learning a lot about C++ programming so I might write some posts about my progress!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/computer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Picture of a laptop monitor with code&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anurag Purkayastha</name></author><summary type="html">This is my blog which will be about a whole heap of tech stuff! From linux to programming to web development to networking! I will be adding posts to this blog as time allows because I am also working ;). I’ll be covering topics that I find particularly interesting. For example, I’m currently learning a lot about C++ programming so I might write some posts about my progress!</summary></entry></feed>